<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Mark Coster</title>
    <link>https://mcoster.net/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Mark Coster</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Mark Coster</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/post/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Magic Science Show!</title>
      <link>https://mcoster.net/post/magic-science-show-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 15:52:02 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcoster.net/post/magic-science-show-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, 12 August, Cohan (a chemistry student) and I performed a &amp;ldquo;Magic Science Show&amp;rdquo; as part of the launch of National Science Week 2017. I&amp;rsquo;ve put together some highlights below:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/fevkPq_1ops&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were really pleased to get a good crowd, with lots of enthusiastic young kids (and their parents) in the audience. I told them that this was our first time performing the show (true!) and that they should watch really closely for anything that went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://mcoster.net/img/magic-science-show-2017/audience.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A good audience for the Magic Science Show!&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I started the show by making myself a &amp;ldquo;chemuccino&amp;rdquo;, telling the audience that it should get really frothy. After much stirring with a wooden-stick, nothing appeared to happen! However, what I had mixed were equal amounts of monomers that react together to make a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyurethane&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;polyurethane&lt;/a&gt;. As the reaction proceeded, a creamy biege foam rose out of the coffee cup, spilling over the sides before hardening.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://mcoster.net/img/magic-science-show-2017/chemuccino.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Starting with a &amp;#39;chemuccino&amp;#39;.&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Acting a somewhat embarrassed that things were going badly already, I told the audience, that we needed a magical blue liquid on the stage for the magic to happen. Cohan brought out a colourless liquid in a sealed bottle, which went deep blue on shaking - magic! The solution contains &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methylene_blue&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;methylene blue&lt;/a&gt;, glucose and sodium hydroxide in water. The latter two components reduce the methylene blue to a colourless form. Shaking the bottle disssolves some oxygen from the headspace above the liquid, which oxidises the methylene blue back to its coloured form. After shaking, as the bottle is left to sit on a table, the methylene blue is reduced again over a period of minutes and the solution returns to colourless. The RSC has a write-up of this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rsc.org/learn-chemistry/resource/res00000729/the-blue-bottle-experiment?cmpid=CMP00005928&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;blue bottle&amp;rsquo; experiment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://mcoster.net/img/magic-science-show-2017/methylene-blue.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The magical blue bottle.&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Under the pretense that we needed a solution on stage that would stay blue, I then set up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belousov%E2%80%93Zhabotinsky_reaction&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Belousov&amp;ndash;Zhabotinsky&lt;/a&gt; reaction. I find these oscillating reactions fascinating because they are so unusual compared to the typical, uni-directional kinetics that we normally see. I told the audience that the reaction should slowly turn a deep blue and stay that way, but instead, it oscillates in a very non-linear fashion between shades of yellow, orange, blue and grey.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://mcoster.net/img/magic-science-show-2017/Belousov.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Setting up the oscillating reaction - not much to see in a still image!&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now a bit exasperated at the inability to maintain a magical blue solution on stage, I set up an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rsc.org/learn-chemistry/resource/res00000744/iodine-clock-reaction?cmpid=CMP00005152&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;iodine clock&amp;rsquo; reaction&lt;/a&gt;. The chemistry involved in this one is a bit easier to explain than the Belousov&amp;ndash;Zhabotinsky reaction. A H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; solution is mixed with a solution of potassium iodide, starch and sodium thiosulfate. I told the audience to watch very carefully because the solution would gradually turn blue. So gradually, they may not notice at first&amp;hellip; The reactions here involve i) oxidation of the iodide to iodine by the hydrogen peroxide, and ii) reduction of the iodine back to iodide by thiosulfate. However, the thiosulfate is limiting, and once it runs out, the iodine liberated reacts with iodide to give I&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/sup&gt; which forms a deep blue complex with starch. In fact, the reaction happens extremely suddenly and the colour is so intense, it looks like the solution instantly goes from colourless to black. This one is my personal favourite:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/iql6r2qLFx0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With yet another failure to make a persistent blue solution for the magic to happen, and being quite thirsty, I demonstrated the &amp;lsquo;rainbow connection&amp;rsquo;. Cohan had previously placed a series of indicators in several wine glasses on the table. Adding a &amp;lsquo;shot&amp;rsquo; of dilute sulfuric acid in ethanol to each glass gives a colourless solution. I then asked the audience to list off the colours of the rainbow - &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ROYGBIV&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ROYGBIV&lt;/a&gt;! I then poured aqueous sodium hydroxide from a jug into each glass, giving a different colour of the rainbow in each one. The indicators are selected to be colourless at low pH and coloured at high pH.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://mcoster.net/img/magic-science-show-2017/rainbow-connection.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;ROYGBIV! Everyone loves colours, don&amp;#39;t they?&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Having now failed to quench my thirst, I tried to pour myself, into a poystyrene cup, a drink of water. Cohan had put a small amount of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sodium_polyacrylate&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;sodium polyarylate&lt;/a&gt; into the cup beforehand. This stuff is amazing! It can absorb up to 300 x its own weight in water, so when I poured myself some water, I pretended to be confused at where the water went, inverting the cup - surprisingly, no water came out! Further portions of water can be added to the cup, which can then be turned upside down, with no water coming out!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://mcoster.net/img/magic-science-show-2017/1200px-Sodium_polyacrylate.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dude, where&amp;#39;s my water?&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        
        &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=4227523&#34;&gt; 
            Image credit: Challiyil Eswaramangalath
        &lt;/a&gt; 
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;With all but one of the magic tricks now spent, we finished the show with the spectacular catalytic decomposition of hydrogen peroxide. To adjacent measuring cylinders containing potassium iodide, detergent and food colouring, was added 30% hydrogen peroxide, resulting in colourful foam columns to end the show. Chromium salts are even more active catalysts, but unfortunately&amp;hellip; carcinogenic!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://mcoster.net/img/magic-science-show-2017/finale.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The finale - foam columns!&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had a great time and the kids in the audience seemed to like it. Hopefully some of them are inspired by science. Big thanks to Cohan for many hours of preparatory work that he did, and for being my side-kick (or was I his side-kick?..) on the day. Also, huge gratitude to the technical staff in Chemistry at Griffith University for their efforts, and my colleagues, past and present who developed the majority of these demonstrations!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A bidirectional synthesis of spiroacetals via Rh(II)-catalysed C-H insertion</title>
      <link>https://mcoster.net/post/bidirectional-spiros/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 16:04:02 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcoster.net/post/bidirectional-spiros/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Molecules where two rings are joined together through a single atom are known as spirocyclic compounds. A particular type, called spiroacetals, are common in biologically-active molecules from nature. We show, for the first time, an efficient new method for making spiroacetals from simple, acyclic starting materials.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://mcoster.net/img/animated-spiro.gif&#34; alt=&#34;animated spiroacetal&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A 5,5-spiroacetal synthesised by this method&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Spiroacetals are exciting molecular scaffolds for discovering new drugs. Our method takes simple acyclic precursors and, by using small amounts of Rh(II) catalysts, converts them into spiroacetals with 3-dimensional structures that make them potentially useful building blocks for drug discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;div style=&#34;height: 400px; width: 500px; position: relative; width: 100%; margin: 0 auto;&#34; class=&#39;viewer_3Dmoljs&#39; data-href=&#39;/pdb/spiro.pdb&#39; data-backgroundcolor=&#39;0xffffff&#39; data-style=&#39;stick&#39;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;A &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; 5,5-spiroacetal synthesised by this method (interactive!)
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mcoster.net/publication/lepage2017/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;This paper&lt;/a&gt; is one of my proudest basic science achievements. It started with an idle wondering about whether these types of compounds could be made &amp;ldquo;backwards&amp;rdquo; compared to how they had been synthesised in the past. The most common methods for spiroacetal synthesis involve formation of the rings through C-O forming reactions. This new work relies on C-C bond-forming events to form the rings. Although the seed of the idea was planted more than ten years ago, it took time to mature, and the end result is, in many respects, much better than the original idea. I particularly enjoyed getting my hands dirty in the lab to play with aspects of this project during a fantastic period of study leave at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mskcc.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center (MSKCC)&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mskcc.org/research-areas/labs/derek-tan/overview&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Prof. Derek Tan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electronic Lab Notebooks (ELN) for the Open Source Malaria (OSM) initiative: A video tutorial</title>
      <link>https://mcoster.net/post/eln-osm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 22:30:02 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcoster.net/post/eln-osm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This video tutorial gives an overview of how to set up and create entries in an Electronic Lab Notebook (ELN). The focus is on how to use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.labtrove.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LabTrove&lt;/a&gt; ELN system to contribute to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://opensourcemalaria.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Open Source Malaria initiative&lt;/a&gt; as a synthetic chemist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/X_tREXdHRE4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using GitHub to contribute to the Open Source Malaria (OSM) initiative: A video tutorial</title>
      <link>https://mcoster.net/post/github-osm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 22:30:02 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcoster.net/post/github-osm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This video tutorial gives an overview of how to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; to contribute to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://opensourcemalaria.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Open Source Malaria initiative&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EK1kxajBfEQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
