<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Presentations on Mark Coster</title>
    <link>https://mcoster.net/tags/presentations/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Presentations on Mark Coster</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Mark Coster</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2017 07:50:02 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/presentations/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>5 Tips for Great Student Presentations</title>
      <link>https://mcoster.net/post/presentation-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2017 07:50:02 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mcoster.net/post/presentation-tips/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I recently spent a couple of weeks assessing final year undergraduate presentations on drug discovery topics. Overall, the standard was excellent, and most of the students seemed to get a lot from the experience. I certainly enjoyed it! However, there&amp;rsquo;s always room for improvement - indeed, I always finish my own presentations with ideas of how I could make it better next time. Here&amp;rsquo;s 5 tips for a great presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-what-are-your-3-key-points&#34;&gt;1. What are your 3 key points?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An audience can only take so much away from any talk, no matter how well crafted. Focus on up to 3 key points. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;No more!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Prepare your whole talk with these three points in mind. Focus on these points in your intro and summary. Make them explicit. When you&amp;rsquo;ve finished your slides, go back through them - how do they relate to the take-home messages you are trying to get across?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-does-your-talk-reflect-the-title&#34;&gt;2. Does your talk reflect the title?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;ve finished your slides, go back to your title - does your talk reflect your title? Eg. If it is &amp;lsquo;Application of technique X to problems Y&amp;rsquo;, do you talk about the technique AND applications? Do your intro and summary slides fully reflect the whole topic?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-practice-practice-practice-practice-at-the-venue&#34;&gt;3. Practice, practice, practice! Practice at the venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some have the &amp;lsquo;gift of the gab&amp;rsquo;, but most will give a better presentation, the more you practice. If possible, &lt;em&gt;test out your presentation in the venue beforehand&lt;/em&gt;. Are all the slides legible from the back row? This is also the perfect place to practice your talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-no-script&#34;&gt;4. No script!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reach the point where you can talk about the slides without reciting from a script. Whether written on the slides, a sheet of paper or memorised, a script normally results in a less engaging talk. Audience engagement is so important and hard to achieve with a scripted speech. Speaker notes are ok, incase you get stuck, but not whole sentences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-turn-up-to-the-venue-early&#34;&gt;5. Turn up to the venue early&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preload your talk, find where the &amp;lsquo;Start presentation&amp;rsquo; button is and go through at least a few slides to make sure everything is working ok. If using a pointing device - practice. Try out the microphone, try out the lights, get used to the stage. Get a friend to sit in the back row and give feedback. On that matter - practice in front of friends, peers, mentors as much as you can and listen to their feedback!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notice&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; that all of my tips relate to preparation - to my mind, that is the biggest differentiator! Good luck, and knock their socks off!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
